（かをり）あたしと　心中しない？
私ね…。
嘘。　言ってみただけ。
"Will you come with me to find out how it ends?"
I'm kidding.
I just thought I'd say it.
You see...
《君は　忘れるの？》
Are you going to forget?
（椿）公生　具合でも悪いの？
Kousei, do you feel sick or something?
（公生）平気。
I'm okay.
（椿）平気そうじゃないから
言ってんの。
I'm asking because you don't look okay.
かをちゃんのお見舞いでも
行こっか。
Why don't we go visit Kao?
ここんところ　みんなで
行けてないじゃない。
We haven't visited her together lately.
It's been a while, so let's all go!
久しぶりに　行こうよ。
（渡）お～　いいね！
I'm in!
僕　行かない。
I'm not going.
（椿）かをちゃんと
ケンカでも　したのかな？
Do you think he got into a fight with Kao?
（柏木）いいの？
あんなこと言って。
Were you okay saying that to him?
（椿）あんなこと？
Saying what?
That was like giving a helping hand to your rival.
敵に　塩を送るみたいなことして。
（椿）敵って…。→
Rival?
音楽のことで　悩んでるんだったら私には　分かんないし。
I don't know how I'd be of any help if it's a problem about music,
たぶん　公生　かをちゃんに会えば
元気になるから。
and I'm sure Kousei will cheer up if he sees Kao.
もっと　本気出してもいいと
思うんだけどな。
I don't think it'll kill you to show him that you're serious.
Who was on your mind while you were reluctantly studying your ass off?
したくもない勉強をしてるのは
誰のため？
志望校のランクを上げたのは？
Who was on your mind when you chose a higher-ranked school?
奥津音大附属近くの高校を
志望したのは　誰のため？
A high school near Okutsu College of Music's High School, no less.
Who was it for?
（椿）ほらっ！　公生は　一人だと
駄目駄目だから。
W-Well, you know! Kousei would be totally lost on his own.
Then be more honest and tell him that yourself.
（柏木）素直に
そう言えばいいのに。　本人にさ。
（椿）ホントはね
行かないでほしいなって思うの。
To tell the truth, I really don't want him leave.
不安だし　イライラする。
It makes me anxious and upset...
嫌みとか　言いたくなるし。
Then I feel like snapping at him.
（椿）《「行かない」って言ったとき
ほっとした　自分がいる》→
When he said he wasn't going,
I was filled with relief
《罪悪感で　いっぱい》
and with guilt.
そんな私を見せたくないから
精いっぱい　カッコつけてるの。
But I don't want him to see me like that,
so I'm trying my hardest to act cool about it.
I don't remember being this awful...
私って　こんな　嫌な女だったかな。
（椿）《幾つもの
知らない自分を発見して→
There are all these different sides of
me that I'm only starting to discover,
幾つもの
知らない自分と向き合う》→
and I have to face all these different sides of me.
《それも　たぶん
恋をするってことなのかな》
But I guess that's also a part of being in love.
（紘子）心　ここにあらずね。
今日は　もういい　帰んな。
Your head is in the clouds.
Let's call it a day.
Go on home.
（公生）すみません。
I'm sorry.
Um, Ms. Seto! Something urgent came up!
（凪）あっ　あの…　瀬戸先生
私　急用が…。
ごめん！　よろしく　お願いね。
Sorry about that! Good luck, okay?
Totsuhara University Hospital
Sumiya City Hall
≪（凪）あれ？　有馬先生。
Oh, it's Arima!
I was making my way down the street casually, but I somehow caught up to you.
ごくごく　普通に歩いてたら
追い付いちゃった。
歩くの遅いです！　姿勢　悪い！
You walk too slow.
And your posture's terrible!
You need to get a grip, or you'll look like a slob!
もっと　しゃきっとしなきゃ！
だらしない！
May your dreams come true
（凪）その　木元がね→
So this guy Kimoto goes all, "I'll dedicate my oboe performance at the culture festival to you, Nagi."
「くる学祭では　凪君のために
オーボエを奏でるよ」→
なんて　言ってくるんです。
とんだ　勘違い野郎です。
He's delusional, seriously!
でも　そういうのが
感激するんじゃないの？
But wouldn't that be pretty thrilling?
heh
It can't be anyone.
It kinda comes down to their looks.
（凪）相手によるな。
フフッ。　現実的だね。
You're such a pragmatist.
やっと　笑った。
I finally got you to laugh!
ありがとう。
ごめんね　心配かけて。
Thanks.
Sorry for making you worry.
べ…　別に　心配なんて…
バカじゃないの！？
N-Not at all. And why would I be worried about you?!
《敵が　貧弱だと
つまんないだけよ》
There's nothing exciting about
having a wimpy enemy, that's all.
（武士）
《あいつ　すげえんだぜ！》→
You know, that guy's unbelievable!
Everyone was freaking out because he nailed the score, but he didn't even bat an eyelash!
《楽譜を完コピして
みんな　ビビってんのに→
眉一つ　動かさねえんだぜ》→
What is he? A gunman out of a Western film?
《西部のガンマンかってぇの》→
《鋼鉄の心臓で
超合金みたいだろ！》→
Or like a die-cast robot with that heart of steel, huh?
《ヒーロみたいだろ！》
Just like a hero!
（武士）《くそっ！》
Damn it!
（凪）《私は　何て言ったらいい？
頑張って　負けないで　なんて→
What am I supposed to tell him?
"Good luck"? "Don't let him beat you"?
無責任な言葉だ》→
But that sounds like an irresponsible thing to say.
Arima Kousei
Sumiya Junior High School
《だから　ありがとうなんて
言わないで》→
So...
You shouldn't thank me.
《何もできなかった　私の
身勝手な　代償行為》→
This is just my selfish way of
compensating for being so powerless.
《単なる　自己満足。
醜い　ファントム》
It was only for my self-satisfaction.
A pathetic phantom.
木元君は　いい演奏家になるね。
Kimoto's gonna be a great performer, you know.
（凪）えっ？　そうですか？
What? You think so?
誰かのために演奏するのは
思ったより　大切なことだよ。
Playing for someone else is more important than you'd think.
《君は　何のために
ピアノを弾くの？》
Why do you play the piano?
《誰かのため？》
Is it for someone else?
君が　ピアノを始めたのも
誰かのためだよね。
You said you started playing the piano for someone else, right?
そういうときは
いい演奏ができた。
Performances like that always go well.
たくさんの人と
音を共有できたとき。
When you've shared your sound with a crowd,
たくさんの人に
音が　届いたとき。
when you've reached that crowd with your sound,
心を重ねたとき。
when your hearts come together...
Music might just be capable of transcending words.
音楽は　言葉を
越えるのかもしれない。
そんなの陳腐です。
女は　現実的なんです。
That's just a cliché.
Women are realistic.
言葉しか　信用しません。
We only believe in words.
May your dreams come true
《ラヴェル…》
Ravel...
《いらっしゃい！》
Welcome!
《聞きたくない　聞きたくない！
ラヴェルなんて　聞きたくない！》
I don't want to hear it! I don't want to hear it!
I don't want to hear any Ravel!
《あたしと　心中しない？》
Come with me to find out how it ends.
（早希）《いらっしゃい》
Welcome.
I don't want to hear it. I don't want to think about anything!
《聞きたくない！
何も　考えたくない！》
《何も　聞こえなくなれば
いいのに》
If only I couldn't hear at all!
Music Preparation Room
≪（渡）よっ。→
Hey!
今から　俺の　かをりちゃんの
お見舞いに行くんだ。→
We're on our way to visit my Kaori in the hospital.
一緒に　行こうぜ。
Come with us.
僕は　いいよ。
You can go without me.
俺たちに　遠慮することねえぞ。
There's no need to be so considerate.
Let's go.
行こうぜ。
行かないってば！
I said I'm not going!
どうしたんだよ？
What's wrong with you?
お前よ
それって　薄情じゃねえ？→
Don't you think you're being cold?
かをりちゃんは　お前に
あんなに　よくしてくれたのに→
After Kaori did so much for you, why are you running away?
何　逃げてんの？
Look at me!
（渡）こっち　向けよ！
（渡）お…　おい　公生。
H-Hey, Kousei...
渡…。
Watari...
僕は　どうしたらいい。
What should I do?
《私ね
あんまり　よくないみたい》
You see...
It's not looking too good for me.
《嘘だ　嘘だ》
It's not true. It's not true.
《ごめんね》
I'm sorry.
I'm making you remember something that you don't want to.
《思い出したくないこと
思い出させちゃって》
《こんななら
会わなきゃよかったね》
It might've been better if we never met, huh?
僕は　何も言えなかった。
I couldn't say a word.
どんな言葉を掛けたらいい？
What could I have said to her?
どんな顔で　会ったらいい？
How should I act when I see her?
なあ　公生。
俺　思うんだけどさ。→
Listen, Kousei.
This is just my opinion, but...
I think you should go see Kaori.
やっぱ　お前は　かをりちゃんに
会いに行くべきだと思うんだ。
そりゃあ　俺なんかで
よけりゃあさ→
I mean, I'd do anything if she was okay with me.
何だってするよ。
好きな子のためなら→
If it was for a girl I liked, I'd even drink muddy water.
泥水だって　すするぞ。
ズズズッとな。→
Straight up and all.
でもよ。　かをりちゃんは　たぶん
俺じゃ　駄目なんだよ。
But you know what? I don't think I'm the one for Kaori.
わがまま言うのも　頼られるのも→
When she wants her own way or a shoulder to lean on...
彼女が
何かしてほしいっていうのは→
Whenever she wants somebody to do something for her, she always turns to you, Kousei.
決まって　お前だよ　公生。
《コンクールに出て…》
Enter a piano competition.
Be my accompanist!
《伴奏しろー！》
I wish I could have some canelé.
《カヌレ　食べたい》
Please support me in this moment that I'm about to lose heart.
《くじけそうになる　私を
支えてください》
でも　何を話していいか
分からないよ。
But I just don't know what to say to her.
んなもん　行ってみりゃ
分かるって。
You'll figure that out once you're there.
A man can only take action!
男は　行動あるのみだ。
僕には　無理だ。
But it's impossible for me.
無理かどうかは
女の子が　教えてくれるさ。
Whether it's impossible or not is up to the girl to decide.
Medication Room
もう　来ないかと思ったわ。
"I didn't think you'd ever come again."
カヌレ　約束してたから。
Well... I promised before that I'd bring some canelés.
Have you been practicing the piano?
ピアノの練習してる？
うん。
Yeah.
学校は？
いつもどおり。
How's school?
The same as usual.
みんな　元気？
まあまあ。
How's everybody doing?
They're fine.
何よ　その返し！
お見舞いする気ないでしょ！
What's with those responses?! Do you even want to be here?!
Hiss
I do!
あるよ！　あるけど…。
Hiss
I do... but I don't know what to say.
何を言えばいいか
分からないだけだ。
昔に　戻るだけだよ。
Things just need to go back to how they were.
忘れちゃえばいいんだよ。
Just forget about it all, like you pressed the reset button.
リセットボタン　押すみたいに
ポチッと。
A click or two is all it'll take.
ポチ　ポチッと。
《何で…》
Why...
《忘れない》
I won't forget.
そしたら　心が軽くなる。
覚えてたって　意味ないもん。
And your heart will feel lighter.
What's the point in remembering, anyway?
弓を持てない　バイオリニストなんて
意味ないもの。
There's no point if the violinist can't even hold her own bow.
《何で…
何で　そういうこと言うの？》
Why...
Why would you say that?
《散々　わめいて　殴り倒して→
After howling at me, knocking me down,
無理やり　僕を
舞台に　引きずり上げたくせに》
and forcefully making me stand onstage...
《散々　忘れたくない風景を
刻みつけたくせに》
After carving so many scenes into my mind that I don't want to forget...
私のカヌレ！
My canelés!
Medication Room
≪いじけたやつに　食わすか！
カヌレが　かわいそうだ！
Like I'd let a cranky whiner like
you eat them! The poor canelés!
But I asked for them!
≪私が　頼んだのに！
≪僕が　買ったんだ！
And I bought them!
≪何よ！
≪何さ！
What's your problem?!
What's yours?!
Not again...
（看護師）また…。
You're irresponsible!
君は　無責任だ。
そんなやつ　もう知らん！
Medication Room
I'm so through with you!
Wait—
待って！
あなたって　ホントに　変な人。
You really are a strange person.
《悔しい　悔しい》
I feel so, so bitter.
《それに　ただ　悲しい》
And I feel just as sad.
《君は　僕に
たくさんのものを　くれたのに→
You gave me so many things.
僕は　君に
何も　してあげられないの？》
Isn't there anything I can do for you?
（渡）《好きな子のためなら
泥水だって　すするぞ》
If it was for a girl I liked, I'd even drink muddy water.
（凪）《気付いてほしい
私がいるって。　私のピアノで》
That's why I want him to notice that I'm here
with my playing.
（小春）《小春が　描いたの》
I drew this.
Your Lie in April
What?! You want to perform at the culture festival?
（凪）えー！？　くる学祭に出たい！？
That came out of nowhere... I don't get it.
（凪）《青天のへきれき
意味　分かんない》→
《何　考えてんの？》
What are you thinking?
You're really pushing it.
また　無茶な。
お願いします。
Please!
Fine.
（凪）いいですよ。
（紘子）嘘！？　あんたの晴れ舞台よ。
No way! But it's your big moment!
Wait, hold on! Are you sure about this?
どうしよう…　ホントに　いいの？
駄目もとだったのに。
ritardando
I only asked because I had nothing to lose.
grave
accidental
（凪）《もっと乞え　有馬　公生》
slur
Grovel some more, Arima Kousei!
diminished
flat
broken consort
atonal
I don't know where this is coming from, but I was struggling
to come up with a program, and this might be interesting.
ちょっと　分かんないけど→
演目　決めあぐねていたし
面白そうなんで。
ありがとう。
Thanks.
有馬先生は　どうして
学祭に　出たいんですか？
Why do you want to perform at the culture festival?
フンッ！　トォッ！
ターッ！
Why, hello, my princess.
やあ　マイ　プリンセス。
Would you care to discuss The Knight of the Rose with me?
僕と　『薔薇の騎士』について
語らないか。
I reserved a diner booth for two!
君のために
ファミレスを予約したよ。
（さつき）凪。
クレープ　食べて　帰ろう。
Nagi, let's have some crêpe on the way home.
Can't!
（凪）無理～！
Is it a date?
（小麦）デート？
Internal  &  Surgical
MAEDA CLINIC
One
Pharmacy
（凪）♪♪「タン　タン　タンタ…」
The sound should have more of a spring to it, so use your wrists to cushion it.
もっと　跳ねるように
手首を使って　柔らかく。
You should try to wait a little bit here,
もう一呼吸　待った方がいいかな。
and speed up the intro while giving variety to the pace.
序盤は　もっと速めで　メリハリを。
（凪）♪♪「タン　タン」
《嘘…　何回　さらったのよ》
No way!
How many times did you go over it?
《昨日より　精度が上がってる》
It's even more accurate than yesterday.
（武士）おっ。　食わねえのか？
You're not eating?
（凪）うん。　ちょっと　食欲ない。
No. I'm not really hungry.
（凪）練習してくる。
I'm gonna go practice.
（武士の母）
あの子　根詰め過ぎじゃない？
Doesn't it seem like she's pushing herself too hard?
I made a mistake! I'm sorry!
（凪）あっ　間違えちゃった！
ごめんなさい。
Don't worry about a wrong note, so just play it through.
ミスタッチは　気にしないで
通していこう。
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
（凪）ごめんなさい　ごめんなさい
ごめんなさい。
（凪の友達）《頑張ってね。
絶対　見に行くからね》
Good luck!
We'll definitely be there!
The spotlight's on you this year!
（教師）
《あなたは　ことしの目玉よ》
Kuru
（教師）《井端先生が
聴きにいらっしゃる》→
Mr. Ibata will be in the audience, so turn in a perfect performance.
《だから　完璧なものをね。
認められれば　一生　安泰だ》
If he acknowledges your talent, you'll be set for life!
（女子生徒）《ライターさんが
来るんだってさ》→
I hear a reporter's coming.
《次世代　美少女ピアニスト特集
だって》
They're going to do a feature on
"a beautiful young female pianist."
Four more days.
（紘子）あと　４日。
望むところだわ。
Bring it on.
（凪）《あと　４日》→
Four more days.
《この曲を　ものにするのに
あと　４日しかない》
I only have four more days to make this piece my own.
（音楽教師）《期待してるわよ》
（男性）《容姿で　得してるよな》
We have high hopes for you!
I bet her looks get her extra points.
The magazine writer's coming just to see Nagi.
（女子生徒）《雑誌ライターは
凪狙いで　来るんだって》
She'll win without even trying.
（男子生徒）《余裕で　トップでしょ》（女子生徒）《ロリコン狙い？》
Acting cute for the attention.
Your parents must be so proud.
（音楽教師）
《親御さんも　鼻が高いぞ》
Good luck!
（友人）《頑張って！》
（女子生徒）《結局　顔だけでしょ》
She's nothing but a pretty face.
I've got to endure this suffering for another four days?
（凪）《あと４日も　この苦しみに
耐えなきゃいけないの？》
（紘子）ちょ…　凪！
≪（ドアの開閉音）
Hey! Nagi!
《助けてよ　お母さん　僕の耳が》
Help me, Mom!
I can't hear!
（紘子）
《つくづく　指導者　失格ね》→
Once again, I'm a failure as an instructor.
I'm about to let history repeat itself.
《また　同じことを
繰り返そうとしている》
凪…。
Nagi.
I'm afraid...
（凪）私　怖いんです。→
学祭の余興なのに
大切な　コンクールなんかじゃないのに。
It's just a school event.
It's not even an important competition.
（紘子）誰だって　怖いよ。
私だって　公生だって。→
We're all afraid.
Even me, even Kousei.
きっと　相座　武士君だって。
And I'm sure even Aiza Takeshi is afraid.
たった数分の舞台に
自分の全てが　集約される。→
Your whole entire life is squeezed into a few minutes onstage.
怖いし　理不尽だよね。
It's scary and unfair.
（凪）じゃあ　どうして　瀬戸先生は
ピアニストを続けてるんですか？
Then why are you still a pianist, Ms. Seto?
その先にね
チャラになる　瞬間がある。
Once you get past that, those feelings will wash away.
All the months of agony, screaming, suffering, and struggling...
悩んで　わめいて　苦しんで
もがき続けた　数カ月。→
There's a moment when you're rewarded for all that.
何もかも報われる　瞬間がある。
《たくさんの人に
音が届いたとき》
When you've reached that crowd with your sound,
《心を重ねたとき》
when your hearts come together...
Music might just be capable of transcending words.
《音楽は
言葉を越えるのかもしれない》
私たちは
その瞬間に　取りつかれた→
Maybe we're creatures who just can't help ourselves, possessed by that moment.
どうしようもない
生き物なのかもしれないね。
It's a little like being in love.
（紘子）《少し　恋と似ている》
（凪）私たち…。
We...
（紘子）捕まえた！
（凪）ギャー！
Gotcha!
Don't monopolize the bathroom!
（紘子）トイレを
占領するんじゃない！→
Mercy! Mercy!
小春！　せめて　左足にしなさい。
Koharu, grab a hold of her left leg!
（紘子）あんたの居場所は
トイレじゃないわ。→
You don't belong in the bathroom.
You're afraid to go out onstage because you practiced so hard.
舞台に立つのが　怖いのは→
あんたが　一生懸命
練習したから。→
身も心も　ピアノに傾けたから。→
You gave your body and soul to the piano,
だから　さらけ出すのが
怖いのよ。→
so that's why you're afraid to expose them.
あんたのことを　「覚悟のない
臆病者」なんて言うやつがいたら→
If there's anyone who'll call you a spineless coward, I'll put an end to them myself.
私が　ぶっ殺してやるわ。
ない胸　張りなさい。→
Puff your chest out, even if you don't have one.
You're Arima Kousei's apprentice!
あんたは　有馬　公生の弟子だよ。
No, I'm not! He's my enemy!
（凪）違います！
あいつは　敵です！
That's the spirit!
（紘子）その意気じゃない。
決着つけようよ　舞台の上で。
Now, let's settle this once and for all onstage.
渡…。
（渡）うん？
Watari?
Huh?
I have a favor to ask.
お願いがあるんだ。
Sure.
いいよ。
まだ　何も言ってないよ。
But I haven't told you anything yet.
If it's you who's asking, it's cool.
お前のお願いなら　いいよ。
Kurumi School Festival
Kuru
School
Festival
This is the scent of pure, musical maidens!
清純派音楽女子の匂いだ！→
Cute girls galore! I've struck gold! Eureka!
カワイイ子臭　充満だ！
キャッホホ～イ！
あんたの存在　海綿体ね。
You're like a walking hard-on.
It's this way, right?
おっ　こっちだな。→
Kotougaoka Concert
Looks like it's already started.
もう始まってるみたいだ。
（武士）せっかく　着ぐるみ
着てるのに　ちまちまと。
Too bad they're plodding along
like that with those costumes on.
（泉）それが　カワイイのよ。
That's what makes them cute.
It's almost Nagi's turn, right?
（泉）もうすぐ　凪ちゃんの出番ね。
仕上がりは　どう？
How did that turn out?
（武士）さあ…　今回は　俺に
何も　教えてくれねえんだよ。
Beats me.
She wouldn't even tell me anything about it.
（泉）ブラコン　卒業かしら。
悲しいわね　お兄ちゃんは。
Could it be that she's outgrown her big brother complex?
As her big brother, it must be heartbreaking.
（武士）清々するよ。
Nah, it's a relief.
（生徒）お疲れ　小麦。
（小麦）ぷはーっ。
Good job, Komugi!
I think I did a good job!
私　よくできました。
あれ？　凪は？
Huh? Where's Nagi?
《なまはげ？》
Is that a namahage?
[ﾏｲｸ]♪♪「悪ぃ子は　いねえが…」
（観客の笑い声）
Kids who love playing mischief...
《大爆笑！？》
The crowd's getting a kick out of this.
That's gonna make a serious act like ours stick out like a sore thumb!
《まともな僕らが　逆に浮いてる》
《恐るべし　くる学祭！》
This school festival is a scary place to be!
≪（凪）♪♪「タン　タン　タン
タタタタタ　タタ…」
大丈夫？
Are you okay?
はぁ！？
だ…　大丈夫に決まってるっしょ！
O-Of course I'm okay! Why wouldn't I be?!
有馬先生こそ　落ち着いてますね。
You're quite calm yourself, Arima!
Lose your head more!
《もっと　うろたえろ》
I guess I'm just so overwhelmed to the extent that I don't feel nervous.
あっけに取られて
緊張する暇が　ないというか。
That's right.
《そうだ　初めて会ったとき
君も　震えてたな》
The first time I met you, your hand was trembling too.
何すんのよ！　エッチ。
セクハラ野郎！
Bam
What are you doing, you pervert?!
I'll call you out on sexual harassment!
Bam
こんなに握り締めて
指が　コチコチになっちゃうよ。
Clenching your hands this hard will lock up your fingers.
手を広げて　力　抜いて。
Open up your hand and let them relax.
We're all afraid.
（紘子）《誰だって　怖いよ。
私だって　公生だって》
Even me, even Kousei.
（凪）《あなたも
追い詰められていたの？》→
Were you driven into a corner too?
Are you afraid too?
《あなたも　怖いの？
私と　同じ？》
The same way I am?
僕の友達が　言ってたよ。
A friend of mine once told me,
「君の人生で　ありったけの君で
真摯に弾けば　いいんだよ」って。
"Just play with sincerity, and put your all
into giving the performance of a lifetime."
でも　私　たった　１３年しか
生きてません。
But I've only lived for thirteen years.
たった　１３年でも　君や
君を見てきた人たちにとって→
Even if it's only been thirteen years,
for you, and for everyone who's watched you till now,
掛け替えのない　１３年だ。
it's thirteen years that can't be replaced.
信じよう。
音楽に傾けた時間を。
Let's believe in the time you've devoted to music.
８番の方
ステージに　お願いします。
Performer No. 8,
please take the stage.
私たちだ。
That's us.
よしっ　行こう。
All right. Let's go!
Right.
はい。
SELECT
FUNCTION
Episode 17
Twilight
Episode 18
When Hearts Come Together
sore zore no yume wo erande
No two dreams can be the same
Episode 18
When Hearts Come Together
sore zore no yume wo erande
No two dreams can be the same
Watch next week too!